A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, M-R FA393
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Richardson, Ralph W.
  In his nearly thirty years with the Rockefeller Foundation (RF), Ralph W. Richardson, Jr. worked as a plant geneticist with the Mexican Agricultural Program (MAP), a program officer in the Agricultural Sciences division, and finally, the head of the Foundation's Quality of the Environment (QE) program. Richardson's intellectual curiosity and penchant for the innovative and unconventional earned him a reputation as a kind of "Renaissance man" within the Foundation.
  Richardson was born on February 2, 1918 in St. Paul, Minnesota, and spent his boyhood on the banks of the Mississippi River at his family's home in Newport, Minnesota. His love of the outdoors and years spent working for plant nurseries and florist businesses as a teenager and college student inspired him to pursue a horticultural career. He completed his undergraduate and graduate studies at the University of Minnesota, earning his B.S. in 1948 and his Ph.D. in horticulture and plant genetics in 1952. His dissertation, "Genetic Effects of Reduced Fertilization in Tomato Flowers," received the 1954 Leonard H. Vaughan Award for "the most outstanding dissertation in vegetable crop breeding published that year in the United States."
  In 1951, the Rockefeller Foundation recruited Richardson to join its Mexican Agricultural Program as an Assistant Plant Geneticist. He worked his way up through the program to Assistant Director (1956-1959) and Director (1959-1962). Richardson's early work with the MAP focused on introducing high-yielding vegetables into Mexican agriculture and improving farmers' cultivation practices. He developed two new tomato varieties ideally suited to Mexican needs--a tomato plant resistant to the grey mold fungus, and a tomato with a firm fruit that could better withstand transportation to market. As Director of the MAP, he helped form Mexico's National Institute of Agricultural Research and served as its Co-Director General, and prepared to transfer the program's work to Mexican colleagues. Richardson also played a central role in the creation of Mexico's International Maize and Wheat Improvement Center, or CIMMYT.
  After eleven years with the Mexican Agricultural Program, Richardson returned to the United States in 1962 to join the Agricultural Sciences Division in the Foundation's New York office. He was promoted from Assistant Director to Associate Director and finally, Deputy Director of the Agricultural Sciences Division in 1970.
  In 1971, Richardson was promoted to Director of Natural and Environmental Sciences, and placed at the helm of the Foundation's newly created Quality of the Environment program. Under his direction, the QE program made grants in environmental studies education, climate research, regional environmental management, and pesticide research, among others.
  When the Foundation's assets plummeted in the economic crisis of the mid-1970s, the QE program was ended. Richardson retired and moved with his wife Amy to State College, Pennsylvania, where he served as an adjunct professor of Agricultural and Environmental Sciences at Penn State. He also took up work as a consultant to the U.S. Department of the Interior, the National Science Foundation, and the National Research Council.
  Richardson died on November 21, 2010, in St. Petersburg, Florida.
  - 1956 October-November (Box 394)
  - 1959 August-1960 February (Box 394)
  - 1960 March-July (Box 394)
  - 1960 August-December (Box 394)
  - 1961 January-July (Box 394)
  - 1961 August-December (Box 394)
  - 1962 January-February (Box 395)
  - 1962 March-May (Box 395)
  - 1962 June-October (Box 395)
  - 1962 November-December (Box 395)
  - 1963 January-February (Box 395)
  - 1963 March-May (Box 395)
  - 1963 June-July (Box 395)
  - 1963 August-December (Box 395)
  - 1964 January-May (Box 396)
  - 1964 June-September (Box 396)
  - 1964 October-December (Box 396)
  - 1965 January-September (Box 397)
  - 1965 June-July (Box 397)
  - 1965 August-September (Box 397)
  - 1965 October-December (Box 397)
  - 1966 January-February (Box 398)
  - 1966 March-April (Box 398)
  - 1966 May-June (Box 398)
  - 1966 July-September (Box 398)
  - 1966 October-December (Box 398)
  - 1967 January-June (Box 399)
  - 1967 July-September (Box 399)
  - 1967 October-December (Box 399)
  - 1968 January-May (Box 399)
  - 1968 June-December (Box 399)
  - 1969 January-October (Box 400)
  - 1969 October-December (Box 400)
  - Index, Diary, 1970 January-February (Box 401)
  - 1970 March-April (Box 401)
  - 1970 May-August (Box 401)
  - 1970 September-October (Box 401)
  - 1970 November-December (Box 401)
  - 1971 January (Box 401)
  - 1971 February-March (Box 401)
  - 1971 April (Box 401)
  - 1971 May-June (Box 402)
  - 1971 July-August (Box 402)
  - 1971 September-December (Box 402)
  - 1972 (Box 402)
  - 1973 (Box 403)
  - 1974 (Box 403)
  - 1975 (Box 403)
  - 1976 (Box 403)
  - 1977 (Box 404)
  - 1978-1980 (Box 404)
  - Index, 1962-1970 (Box 404)
- Ritcher, Paul O.
  - 1958-1959 (Box 404)
- Robbins, William J.
  - 1929-1930 (Box 405)
    See also Wilbur E. Tisdale and E. W. Lindstrom, May 1928-January 1929.
- Roberts, Lewis M.
  - 1952-1955 August (Box 405)
  - 1955 September-1957 (Box 405)
  - 1958 (Box 405)
  - 1960 January-March (Box 406)
  - 1960 April-August (Box 406)
  - 1960 September-December (Box 406)
  - 1961 January-April (Box 406)
  - 1961 May-July (Box 406)
  - 1961 August-December (Box 406)
  - 1962 January-April (Box 407)
  - 1962 May-August 2 (Box 407)
  - 1962 August 3-October (Box 407)
  - 1962 November-December (Box 407)
  - 1963 January-February (Box 408)
  - 1963 March-May (Box 408)
  - 1963 June-September (Box 408)
  - 1963 October-December (Box 408)
  - 1964 January-March (Box 409)
  - 1964 April-June (Box 409)
  - 1964 July-October (Box 409)
  - 1964 November-December (Box 409)
  - 1965 January-April (Box 409)
  - 1965 May-September (Box 409)
  - 1965 October-December (Box 409)
  - 1966 January-February (Box 410)
  - 1966 March-May (Box 410)
  - 1966 June-September (Box 410)
  - 1966 October-December (Box 410)
  - 1967 January-March (Box 410)
  - 1967 April-August (Box 410)
  - 1967 September-October (Box 410)
  - 1967 November-December (Box 410)
  - 1968 (Box 411)
  - 1969 (Box 411)
  - 1970 (Box 412)
  - 1971 (Box 412)
  - 1972 (Box 412)
  - 1973 (Box 413)
  - Trips to Honduras, Guatamala, 1973 December (Box 413)
  - 1974 January-August (Box 413)
  - Trips to Amazon, 1964, 1969, 1971, 1977 (Box 413)
- Robertson, William van B.
  - 1967 (Box 413)
- Rogers, Thomas E.
  - 1964-1966 (Box 414)
- Rohde, Jon E.
  - 1973-1976 (Box 414)
  - 1977 (Box 414)
- Rose, Wickliffe
  Born in Tennessee in 1862, Wickliffe Rose devoted much of his life to modernizing the American South and to public health work around the world. A professor of history and philosophy by training, Rose began his career teaching at Peabody College and the University of Nashville. In 1910 he joined the Southern Education Board, an organization devoted to remedying the problems of public education in the American South. He remained with the organization until 1915.
  Rose's association with Rockefeller organizations began in 1910 with his appointment as Executive Secretary of the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission (RSC). In this role he directed a massive and successful public health campaign to eradicate hookworm disease in the Southern United States. In its first five years the campaign examined nearly 1.5 million people and provided treatment for 500,000 patients. The campaign was also responsible for the overall improvement of sanitary conditions in the South and for making significant inroads in the improvement of state and local health services. The success of the campaign had major ramifications for improved economic and educational conditions in the South, and the lessons learned during that campaign were applied in subsequent hookworm eradication campaigns worldwide.
  As a result of his success with the RSC, Rose was appointed one of the original trustees of the Rockefeller Foundation in 1913. He also served as Chairman of the War Relief Commission from 1914 to 1917 and General Director of the International Health Division (IHD) from 1915 to 1923. As Chairman of the War Relief Commission, he directed support for European refugees, tracked the spread of diseases such as typhus across Europe and administered monetary support for military hospitals devoted to the problems of battlefield wounds and infections. In his role at IHD, Rose applied skills learned during the hookworm campaign to other major global public health campaigns, including research into the causes and eradication of yellow fever. Rose also helped to found public health schools at Johns Hopkins University and Harvard and assisted in the founding the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine.
  Following his tenure with the IHD, Rose served as President of the both the General Education Board (GEB) and the International Education Board (IEB) in 1923. In these roles he once again devoted his talents to improving educational opportunities for both white and African-American students in the American South. Rose retired from his work with the RF in 1928, and he died in 1931.
  - 1911 Rockefeller Sanitary Commission - Itineraries of the Administrative Secretary, Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rose, Wickliffe (Reel M Ros 1, Frame 1, Box 415)
    Rose reports on county dispensaries in Marion county, Mississippi and Alabama.
    Rural population; Public health; United States; Sanitation; Hookworm disease; Dispensaries; Mississippi; Hygiene; Alabama
  - 1911 Itinerary of the Administrative Secretary though Northern Neck, Viriginia, June 1911; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rose, Wickliffe
    Rose reports on hookworm disease in Northern Neck, Virginia.
    United States; Virginia; Rural population; Sanitation; Hygiene; Public health; Dispensaries; Hookworm disease
  - 1911 Itinerary of the Administrative Secretary through Columbus, Robeson, Sampson and Halifax Counties, North Carolina, July 1911; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rose, Wickliffe
    Sanitation; United States; Public health; Rural population; Hygiene; North Carolina; Dispensaries; Hookworm disease
  - 1912 Itinerary of the Administrative Secretary through Bell county, Kentucky, October 1912; Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease; Rose, Wickliffe
    United States; Sanitation; Rural population; Public health; Kentucky; Hygiene; Hookworm disease; Dispensaries
  - 1913 International Health Commission - Notes on the Journey to England and the West Indies, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission; Rose, Wickliffe (Reel M Ros 1, Frame 58, Box 415)
    Saint Lucia; Public health; Hygiene; Hookworm disease; Grenada; England; Barbados; Antigua; Saint Vincent; Sanitation; Trinidad; West Indies
  - 1914 Itinerary of the Director General through the Federation Malay States, May 1914; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission; Rose, Wickliffe (Box 415, Reel M Ros 1, Frame 131)
    Rose travels to the Federated Malay States to survey government and estate hospitals, and determine the present efforts to combat hookworm disease. The diary includes itinerary through the Philippine Islands.
    Philippines; Public health; Sanitation; Hookworm disease; Hygiene; Malaria; Malaysia
  - 1914 Diary Notes, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission; Rose, Wickliffe
    The diary includes notes on trips to England and Egypt; program of relief, control and prevention of Hookworm disease in Sri Lanka; notes on the malaria program, and notes on sanitation and hookworm disease in Malay and survey conditions in the Philippines.
    Venereal diseases; United States; Tropical medicine; Sri Lanka; Singapore; Public health; Sanitation; Malaria; Malaysia; Hookworm disease; Japan; Egypt; England
  - 1915, Rose, Wickliffe; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission (Reel M Ros 1, Frame 190, Box 415)
    The diary documents an interview regarding disease prevention in Turkey.
    Hygiene; Hookworm disease; Medicine, Preventive; Malaria; Sanitation; Public health; United States; Turkey
  - 1916 The Situation in Mexico and the Possibilities of Cooperation with the International Health Board, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission; Rose, Wickliffe (Reel M Ros 1, Frame 235, Box 415)
    The diary documents a conference held with Senior Cabrera of Mexico to discuss cooperation with Rockefeller Foundation to help control Typhus Fever in Mexico.
    Malaria; Mexico; Hookworm disease; Hygiene; Yellow fever; Public health; Sanitation
  - 1917 Conference with Peter Goldsmith, January 29, 1917; Rose, Wickliffe; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission (Box 415, Reel M Ros 1, Frame 244)
    In an interview with Goldsmith, he discusses his travels to South America as a representative of the Department of Education and Intercourse of the Carnegie Foundation for Peace to survey their local education and establish personal relations with leaders of public opinion.
    South America; United States; Public health; Sanitation; Hygiene
  - 1918 Conferences in Washington, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission; Rose, Wickliffe (Reel M Ros 1, Frame 248, Box 415)
    Malaria; Public health; Agriculture; Hygiene; Yellow fever; United States; Tuberculosis; Sanitation
  - 1919, Rose, Wickliffe; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission (Box 415, Reel M Ros 1, Frame 295)
    The IHB cooperates with governments throughout the world in demonstrating the feasibility and economic value of preventive measures against disease and creating popular interest and support for public health work. The diary documents the campaign against Tuberculosis in France, Malaria work in Italy and manufacturing oil of chenopodium.
    Nursing; Jaundice; Hygiene; Hookworm disease; United States; Sanitation; Public health; France; Europe; Communicable diseases; Agriculture
  - Index, 1920; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission; Rose, Wickliffe (Reel M Ros 2, Frame 1, Box 415)
    1920 Index; 4 pages
    Sanitation; Public health; South America; Belgium; France; Europe; Hygiene; Holland (Netherlands: Province)
  - 1920, Rose, Wickliffe; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission (Reel M Ros 2, Frame 5, Box 415)
    The grants, visits and interviews with professionals in the field of public health focus on prevention of disease. The diary includes updates on International Health Board projects, malaria control through quinine, discussions of effects of World War I and a conference between Dr. Heiser and Dr. Rose regarding South America.
    Public health; Hygiene; Malaria; France; Holland (Netherlands: Province); Medicine, Preventive; Nursing; Medical education; Medicine; Sanitation; South America; Tropical medicine; Tuberculosis; Europe; Dispensaries; Communicable diseases; Belgium; World War I; Yellow fever
  - Index, 1921; Rose, Wickliffe; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission (Box 415, Reel M Ros 2, Frame 152)
    1921 Index; 9 pages
    Sanitation; United States; Hygiene; Public health
  - 1921, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission; Rose, Wickliffe (Reel M Ros 2, Frame 161, Box 415)
    The grants, visits and interviews with professionals in the field of public health focus on prevention of disease through new national health services and new ministries of health. The diary also documents yellow fever discussions.
    Yellow fever; United States; Tuberculosis; Tropical medicine; Sanitation; Public health; Malaria; Hookworm disease; Hygiene
  - Index, 1922-1923 (Box 415, Reel M Ros 2, Frame 412)
  - 1922, Rose, Wickliffe; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission (Reel M Ros 2, Frame 418, Box 415)
    The grants, visits and interviews with professionals in the field of public health focus on prevention of disease.
    Hygiene; Yellow fever; Sanitation; Public health
  - 1923-1924 Index, Rose, Wickliffe; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Commission
    1923-1924 Index; 6 pages
  - 1922 Index Log of Journey to Europe, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Rose, Wickliffe
    Index Log of Journey to Europe; 5 pages
    Tropical medicine; Sanitation; Public health; Malaria; Hygiene; Europe
  - 1922 Diary, Including Log of Journey to Europe, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Rose, Wickliffe (Box 415, Reel M Ros 2, Frame 438)
    Diary Log of Journey to Europe- Includes memorandum of visits and malaria survey in Italy.
    Malaria; Public health; Ireland; Italy; Europe; Hygiene; England; Sanitation; Tropical medicine
  - 1922 5 May- 30 December, Rose, Wickliffe; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board
    This diary of Wickliffe Rose documents a trip to London and includes various updates on International Health Board programs.
    Yellow fever; Tropical medicine; United States; Public health; Sanitation; Hygiene; Malaria
  - 1923-1924 Index, Rose, Wickliffe; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board
    Index of countries and Cities Visited and of Institutions and Organizations Mentioned in Log; 12 pages
    Hygiene; Sanitation; Public health
  - 1923 December- 1924 April, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Board; Rose, Wickliffe (Reel M Ros 2, Frame 741, Box 416)
    Index of Names of Persons Mentioned; 6 pages. Itinerary from December 1923- April 1924 in connection with work of the International Education Board. The diary surveys agricultural education and research laboratories in Europe.
    Holland (Netherlands: Province); Hungary; France; Germany; England; Europe; Denmark; Education; Bulgaria; Czechoslovakia; Austria; Belgium; Agriculture; Ireland; Italy; Norway; Poland; Scotland; Spain; Sweden; Switzerland; Yugoslavia
- Rupert, Joseph A.
  South America; Central America; Mexico
  - 1955-1957 (Box 417)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 417)
  - Diary Duplicate, 1959 (Box 417)
  - 1960-1962, 1964, 1966 (Box 417)
- Rusk, Dean
  While mostly remembered for his career in government, Dean Rusk was also a distinguished university professor and an influential president of the Rockefeller Foundation (RF).
  Dean Rusk was born in Cherokee County, Georgia, in 1909. He attended Davidson College and was selected as a Rhodes Scholar. Upon graduation, he began a career in teaching as an associate professor of government at Mills College, where he was later named Dean of Faculty. While at Mills, he simultaneously pursued a law degree at the University of California, Berkeley Law School and graduated in 1940.
  In 1940 Rusk jointed the United States Army as an infantry reserve captain. He participated in the Burma campaigns during World War II and was promoted to Assistant Chief of Staff in the Operations Division of the General Staff. Following the end of the war, he joined the State Department as Assistant Chief of the Division of International Security Affairs, before going on to become Assistant to the Secretary of War and Director of the Office of United Nations Affairs in the State Department. In 1949 he was named Deputy Under Secretary of State, and in 1950 he was named Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs under President Harry Truman. He held this position during an era of tense international relations in the Far East, including the outbreak of the Korean War.
  In 1952 Rusk left government service to preside over the RF. He had served on the Foundation's Board of Trustees since 1950. During his tenure as president, the RF devoted more and more of its resources to the problems of the developing world, at a critical moment when many nations were emerging from colonial rule. Work in agriculture began to supplant the foundation's long-standing interests in global health.
  Rusk left the RF in 1961 when he was offered the position of Secretary of State under President John F. Kennedy. From the Bay of Pigs invasion to the Cuban missile crisis and the beginning of the Vietnam War, he influenced some of the defining political moments of the twentieth century. Following Kennedy's assassination in 1963, he continued to serve as Secretary of State under Lyndon Johnson. He held the post for a total of eight years, leaving at the end of the Johnson administration.
  Following his departure from the Department of State, Rusk returned to the RF as its first Distinguished Fellow. This year-long position gave him the freedom to purse his own academic interests and time to redirect his career.
  Rusk eventually returned to academia, becoming a professor of international law at the University of Georgia from 1970 to 1984. He died in Athens, Georgia in 1994.
  - 1952-1960 (Box 417)
- Russell, Frederick F.
  Frederick F. Russell was directly responsible for introducing the typhoid vaccine to United States Army troops in 1910. His success with the vaccination program and his expertise in preventive medicine informed his subsequent contributions to the international health programs of the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) from 1919 to 1935.
  Russell was born in Auburn, New York, in 1870. A graduate of Cornell University and the College of Physicians and Surgeons at Columbia University, he was also educated at the University of Berlin. Following a commission in the United States Army Medical Corps, he first began to conduct research on typhoid vaccinations. In 1907 this research led to his appointment as Curator of the Army Medical Museum and instructor at both the Army Medical School and George Washington University. In 1917 he went on to earn a Doctor of Science degree from George Washington University.
  In 1908, on behalf of the of the Surgeon General and the Army, Russell visited medical researchers in London and Berlin to observe vaccination experiments using live typhoid organisms to protect against transmission of that disease. Upon his return, he recommended emulating that approach and received support to establish a vaccine laboratory to conduct more tests. He then developed and implemented the Army's highly successful typhoid vaccination program.
  The success with the typhoid vaccine program and his leadership of the military medical laboratories during World War I and later in the Panama Canal Zone brought Russell to the attention of Wickliffe Rose, director of the RF's International Health Board (IHB). In 1919 Rose hired Russell to develop the IHB's public health laboratory service. Upon joining the RF and resigning from the Army, he was promoted to Brigadier General in the Medical Reserve Corps. When Rose stepped down as IHB director in 1923, Russell replaced him and retained that position when the International Health Division (IHD) replaced the IHB in 1927.
  Russell originally promoted laboratories for public health diagnostic work and later emphasized the importance of scientific research to improve public health and to serve as the basis for successful disease control programs, such as those run by the RF for malaria and yellow fever. This focus on laboratories and research often put Russell at loggerheads with other members of the RF staff who sought to support more applied health programs. According to the scientist and scholar John Farley, Russell "was far too confident and powerful to worry about what was going on behind his back. With his authoritative bearing and military manner… (He) established few personal relationships with his colleagues." Yet, "under his direction the Health Division's morale remained high and it reached the pinnacle of its power and influence."[1]